Mathetican Society Records UA079
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Mathetican Society Records
1854 -- 1962
1854 -- 1892
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Mathetican Society
UA079
0.75 Linear Feet 2 boxes
Arrangement
This collection is organized into one series: Mathetician Society records.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains minutes, reports, ledgers, printed programs and orations, and correspondence of the Mathetican Society. Most of the material is in bound volumes.
Biographical / Historical
The Mathetican Society was created in 1854, and was the leading undergraduate literature and debate club for the first four decades after the opening of Tufts College. Thomas H. Angell, A1858, led the effort to found the Mathetican Society, which became the first student society at Tufts College. It soon became a literary organization typical of those flourishing on almost every college campus in the nineteenth century. Mathetican Society meetings were serious affairs with formal programs that included debates, essays, orations, and poems on topics such as taxes, women's suffrage, and world peace. The Mathetican Society had two annual traditions. Every October, the Society held a special exercise in recognition of its anniversary. Until 1875, the Mathetican Society also had the privilege of creating a formal program to follow the annual commencement ceremony for graduates and their families. As the popularity of fraternities and other organizations began to grow on campus, the Mathetican Society began to falter. Membership waned, and in 1896, the Mathetican Society officially disbanded, transferring its entire treasury to the Tufts Debating Union.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Student life; Student Activities -- Student Government, Clubs, and Organizations; Student Activities -- Student Publishing; Student life
- Mathetician Society records, 1854 -- 1962; 1854 -- 1892; UA079.001; 0.75 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains minutes, reports, ledgers, printed programs and orations, and correspondence. Most of the material is in bound volumes.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged by type of record, then chronologically.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open for research.
  - Mathetican Society constitution, bylaws, and members, 1855 -- 1872; UA079.001.001.00001 (Box 1)
  - Constitution, members, reports of secretaries, 1883 -- 1885; UA079.001.001.00002 (Box 1)
  - Secretary's record book, 1854 -- 1863; UA079.001.001.00003 (Box 1)
  - [Secretary's] Record book, 1863 -- 1874; UA079.001.001.00004 (Box 1)
  - Secretary's record book, 1874 -- 1878; UA079.001.001.00005 (Box 1)
  - Clippings, 1855 -- 1962; UA079.001.002.00001 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1857 -- 1861; UA079.001.002.00002 (Box 2)
  - Oration and poem, 1856; UA079.001.002.00003 (Box 2)
  - Programs, 1857 -- 1878; UA079.001.002.00004 (Box 2)
  - Mathetican Society Resolutions, 1873 -- 1878; UA079.001.002.00005 (Box 2)
  - Constitution, 1892; UA079.001.002.00006 (Box 2)
  - Treasurer's Book, 1855 -- 1873; UA079.001.002.00007 (Box 2)
  - Treasurer's account book, 1874 -- 1878; UA079.001.002.00008 (Box 2)